Before our next speaker, I'm going to make
one comment. A lot of people don't know
this. I'm not going to say which company.
We have had the first company that is now
reincorporating in Utah because of what
we're doing with SEDI. I'm not going to
say what state they're leaving from, but
this is a valuable economic, it's a value
add. People will come to your state
because they want privacy. People are
crazy. craving this type of freedom. So
you can think about that. What is it that
this offers that other states or other
countries can offer? And it really will be
an export, but it's going to attract
people to your state. And I think for all
of you, the message is resounding. This is
something people want. We just have to
work through and figure out how we're
going to get there. All right. The last
comments we are going to hear from, I
think this is probably the coolest person
we have in attendance today. So we have
Scott Stornetta, a co-inventor of the
blockchain and mentioned in the Satoshi
paper, for Bitcoin. Sorry, where do we
have Scott? Oh, right here in front.
I think Stuart, my co-inventor, is
actually the coolest person here. I'm
Scott Stornetta and I speak for the trees.
Actually not. I just for years wanted a
situation because I'm such a Dr. Seuss fan
to be able to give that line, but
whatever. I am grateful for the
opportunity to speak briefly.
By way of introduction, Dr. Haber and I
began an effort more than 30 years ago at
Bell Communications Research, part of the
old Bell Labs family. As research
scientists, we published an influential
paper outlining a method to create
immutable digital records through widely
witnessed public events through widely
witnessed events made public. This is what
we now call a blockchain. While I don't
endorse any specific cryptocurrency or
blockchain application, the data integrity
mechanisms that Stuart and I pioneered
have proven reliable and they now
safeguard over $3 trillion in digital
assets. That's trillion with a T. What
does this have to do with identity? Well,
let me address it first philosophically
and then technically. Philosophically, the
SEDI initiative holds that a person's
digital identity is an inherent human
right in the digital age, created and
controlled by the individual. Yet, as
Locke and Rousseau argued, individuals
choose to enter a social contract with a
community governed by the state. This
creates a need to link personal identity
with state requirements, hence the concept
of state-endorsed digital identity.
Technically, this aligns very well with
the principles Stuart and I use to
construct the blockchain. To build trust
in immutable records without relying on
any single third party, we spread the
trust mechanism across the user community.
This is what is now commonly described as
the principle of decentralization.
Similarly, decentralizing digital
identity, keeping it under individual
control, well reflects the inalienable
rights. You know, they wanted to correct
Thomas Jefferson and call those
unalienable rights, but Virginia prevailed
on that one. Inalienable rights
articulated in America's Declaration of
Independence and echoed in many
declarations of human rights both in
Europe and in varying degrees throughout
the world. I must emphasize that I did not
participate in any of the work leading to
this summit. So I'm offering an outsider's
perspective. Born in Maryland and a New
Jersey resident for over 30 years, my view
is not Utah-centric. though I do confess
my wife is from Ogden and Dr. Haber
similarly confesses that he has at least
flown over the state in route from New
York to California many times. Okay. Point
is we've been entirely external to the
process, the legislation and the technical
details. With that said, I endorse this
effort. Not because I agree with every
part of the legislation or descriptions.
because no initiative is perfect at birth.
And this one is evolving. I invite you to
listen to a later speaker today, Scott
Kelly, who will talk about the word
iterative. I'm a fan of it. But we
shouldn't let the perfect be the enemy to
the good. And so I invite you, especially
those from other states, to join this
call. Not because it's flawless, but
because your involvement can refine it.
Not because you fully agree politics is
the art of the possible and it often
requires compromise but not compromise of
principle. But because good people united
at a good cause can achieve more together.
I close with a unifying phrase from late
17th century Europe originally in Latin
but I will spare you that part. in
necessary things unity in undecided things
liberty and in all things charity if we're
guided by this principle i'm confident
that we collectively can achieve something
of value to many many people across